Finding Aid for Clarence E. Brewer papers, 1914-1964
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Clarence E. Brewer papers 1914-1964
Brewer, Clarence E., 1892-1964.
1 phonograph records
2 linear feet
85786 Aa 2
Pioneer in the public recreation movement, Detroit (Mich.) Recreation Commissioner. Correspondence, memoranda, and printed matter relating to the work of the War Camp Community Service program in the 1920's.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of David Brewer (donor no. 5560 )
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Clarence Brewer was one of the leading pioneers of the public recreation movement in the United States during the first half of the twentieth century. He is known in Michigan primarily for his recreation work in Detroit where he served as Commissioner of Recreation (1920-1940) and General Superintendent of Parks and Recreation (1920-1942). From 1943 to 1961, Brewer served as a field representative with the National Recreation Association (first in New York and later in the Great Lakes area). During his tenure with the N.R.A. he gained national prominence for his work in promoting community, industrial, and military recreational programs.
Prior to arriving in Detroit in 1920, Brewer held posts in the recreation departments of a number of cities, including Columbus, Ohio (1910, 1914-1917) and Racine, Wisconsin (1917). He also worked for two years (1919-1920) as a community recreation organizer with the War Camp Community Service (W.C.C.S.), which was organized during World War I (May, 1917) by the Playground and Recreation Association of America at the request of the United States War Department. The original purpose of the W.C.C.S. was to provide constructive leisure time activities for servicemen by developing the recreation facilities of communities near the training camps in which they were stationed. Within a short time the program was expanded to include service to civilian defense workers. At the height of the war period, the W.C.C.S. operated in more than six hundred communities. With the end of the war period (June 1919) the emphasis of the W.C.C.S. (now shortened in name to "Community Service") shifted to developing recreation activities for the general public.
In 1930 the Playground and Recreation Association of America merged with several other recreational organizations to form the National Recreation Association. Community Service continued operations under the auspices of the NRA during the depression years. It was also quite active in developing recreation programs for both military and civilian personnel during World War II.
The Clarence Brewer collection is valuable for anyone doing research on the development of the community recreation movement in the United States during the early twentieth century. Unfortunately, the Brewer collection contains very little material relating to the development of community recreation in Detroit. This is strange considering Brewer's long association with the City (1920-1941), first as Commissioner of Recreation and later as General Superintendent of Parks and Recreation. His personal papers do contain frequent reference to Detroit; the bulk of these, however, are concerned with such things as salary negotiations and civil service examinations. The extant material falls into three distinct series: Personal papers; other recreation and related organizations; and War Camp Community Service.
Subjects:
Detroit (Mich.). Recreation Commission.; National Recreation Association.; Recreation.; War Camp Community Service (U.S.)
- Personal materials
  The personal materials series - mostly correspondence covering the period from 1914 to 1963 -- largely relates to Brewer's activities as a community recreation organizer for the War Camp Community Service (i.e., W.C.C.S.) from 1919 to 1920. A great deal of material also relates to his activities as a field representative with the National Recreation Association (1943-1961). Prominent among the N.R.A. material is a large group of community recreation surveys which Brewer conducted during the late 1940's and early 1950's.
  - Correspondence 1915-1962, undated, 23 folders (Box 1)
  - War Camp Community Service
    - Activities in Hamilton, Ohio November 1919-April 1920 (Box 1)
    - Activities in Zanesville, Ohio April 1920-October 1920 (Box 1)
  - Health and insurance records (Box 1)
  - Speeches 1948-1961 (Box 1)
  - Recreation surveys of various U.S. cities conducted by Brewer as a field representative with the National Recreation Association 1947-1951 (Box 1)
  - Teaching records (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous personal papers (Box 1)
  - Dedication ceremonies relating to "Clarence E. Brewer Recreation Center and Playground," Detroit, Michigan October, 1965 (Box 1)
  - Newspaper clippings (Box 1)
  - Talk, WHLS, Port Huron June 1958, 1 vinyl disc (Box 1)
- Other recreation and related organizations
  The other recreation and related organizations series relates to the recreation activities of various U.S. cities (but not directly connected with Brewer or the W.C.C.S.) during the period from 1915 to about 1955. This series includes constitutions, annual reports, and miscellaneous printed material of several private and municipal recreation organizations. There are also publications of regional and national associations (such as the Northeast Recreation Association and the American Association of Park Superintendents).
  - American Association of Park Superintendents Yearbook for 1918 (Box 1)
  - Americanization programs (pamphlets and printed materials) (Box 1)
  - Camp Fire Girls (pamphlets and printed materials) (Box 1)
  - Detroit, Michigan. Recreation activities circa 1915-1930 (Box 1)
  - Northeast Recreation Association (Box 1)
  - Temperance: typescript of speech by Raymond Calkins entitled "Substitutes for the Saloon" (Box 1)
  - Recreation activities in various U.S. cities 1920s-1950s (Box 1)
    (not related to Brewer or the W.C.C.S.)
  - Surveys (recreation) (Box 1)
  - Detroit, Michigan. Cobo Arena: Miscellaneous convention material 1958 (Box 1)
  - Trade catalogues (playground equipment) (Box 1)
- War Camp Community Service
  The largest series of material relates to the activities of the War Camp Community Service. In addition to a large number miscellaneous publications (such as pamphlets, folders, policy statements, and report forms), there are substantial runs of official serial bulletins. Also included are materials relating to the activities of the Playground and Recreation Association of America (W.C.C.S.'s parent organization) (1909-1920) and the National Recreation Association (1941-1961).
  - Bulletins 1919-1920, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Bulletins 1920-1921, 12 folders (Box 2)
  - Community Organizers Bulletins, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Community Organizers for Singing Bulletins (Box 2)
  - W.C.C.S. Bulletins (War Camp Community Service Workers) 1919-1920 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous Bulletins (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous printed material 1918-1925
    - 1918-1925 (Box 2)
      (include pamphlets, song books, and war memorial tributes)
    - 1919-1921 (Box 2)
      (include special bulletins, policy statements, and organizational procedures)
  - Sample report forms undated (Box 2)
  - Training Schools 1919-1920 (Box 2)
    (include program schedule for first training school and minutes of second training school)
  - Activities in various U.S. cities circa 1920s (Box 2)
  - Playground and Recreation Association of America
    (parent organization of W.C.C.S., name later changed to National Recreation Association)
    - Bulletins 1919-1921 (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous printed material 1916-1919 (Box 2)
    - Printed pamphlets relating to programs, philosophy, and policy 1909-1920 (Box 2)
    - National Recreation Association printed material
      - 1941-1950 (Box 2)
      - 1958-1961 (Box 2)